we're here to talk about the journey to
becoming a staff engineer in a large C
company and so we'll go through our
intros and talk about which companies we
have experience in in just a minute but
just to give some context I wanted to
quickly share this diagram from levels
FYI what does it mean to be a staff
engineer staff engineer is a very senior
level at these tech companies so
typically you get to a senior level
that's a terminal level of being an
individual contributor an IC engineer
and so that's what you can look at here
which is senior s L5 at Google E5 at
Facebook S3 at Amazon the level after
that is typically what we're referring
to when we talk about staff engineering
so staff s at Google is L6 E6 at
Facebook at Amazon interestingly there's
no notion there's no vocabulary for a
staff engineer the level after senior is
principal so keep that in mind we're
going to we talk about this from the
perspective of Staff engineer but the
vocabulary does differ based off of what
company you're at but generally the idea
of staff is that you have influence and
scope across multiple teams and perhaps
even companywide so it is a very
challenging level to perform at and I
think it'll be really valuable to hear
from everyone here about how they
achieve that and you know what advice
they would have for everyone here so to
kick off the intros do anyone want to
start maybe Lee do you want to kick us
off so I'm Lee mck I have been working
in some capacity in software engineering
since 2004 that's when I finished an
undergraduate degree so worked at some
smaller companies for a while did
Healthcare informatics did nonprofit
fundraising stuff and then starting in
2012 worked at Amazon worked as an sd2
there for a lot of the time moved into
people management got promoted L6 which
is equivalent to senior engineer as a
manager and then a couple of years ago
left Amazon joined it was then Facebook
became meta while I was there as an L6
engineer staff they don't like things
but same as staff level elsewhere didn't
have a super fun time didn't go great so
about a year and a half ago I moved over
to Google in the same capacity working
as an IC as a staff engineer um I've
worked on the chat product and now I'm
over on Gmail working on notifications
I'm sure we'll give this General
disclaimer but I'm not speaking on
behalf of Google no one is speaking on
behalf of their employers so my name is
Ryan Peterman I'm a Staff engineer at
meta and my prior experience is that I
graduated from utila in 2017 I worked in
a small satellite office at Amazon for
around eight months or so and then I
started I've met a at the new grad level
and since then I got promoted to staff
and a few years and I'm still at meta
right now working on the Instagram
product I'm just gonna Note new College
hire is L3 there so that is three
promotions in five years so just pretty
significant anyway Ryan you pick next
awesome yeah that's exactly right all
three or ic3 or E3 for the newr level
I'll pass it to Kari hey thanks Ken hey
everyone my name is Carly I currently
work at Activision same thing as Le I'm
speaking on behalf of Activision but I
am currently a senior manager but I also
still hold an IC title which is a fun
time so I do both my IC title is
equivalent to staff we call it like lead
engineer yeah I guess I graduated I
finished grad school in 2017 moved up
from Junior data scientist fairly
quickly started at Activision at the
senior level actually and then took
about two years to get up to lead so
it's been a fun ride making video games
I love it I work in security so there's
a lot that I can't answer about
specifics about my job but I'm happy to
give as many examples as I can not going
to tell us how to write
a
around oh that would be great all right
Zach All right so for me I started my
journey in big Tech at Facebook back
when it was Facebook back in 2016 doing
like data engineering kind of stuff and
I think I'm one of the ones here I think
me and Lee I guess are the ones who like
did the journey like through a bunch of
hops but then I went to Netflix I feel
like Netflix is where I got to staff but
like back then Netflix didn't have staff
everyone was just a senior engineer but
what I was working on there was really
crazy I also worked in security like
Carly when I worked at Netflix and then
I got the official staff title when I
jumped to Airbnb and there I worked for
two years I recently left I left about
six months ago now I'm doing like
content full-time but it's a fun fun gig
I'm been liking it yeah rul you're next
yeah all right I'm Rahul I am here at
the Bay Area unlike everyone here other
than Zach I do speak for my employer
because my employer is me taro I'm very
transparent and open happy to be open
about what was my experience like at
meta and Pinterest which is where I work
and also my kind of perspective as a
somewhat of Outsider now looking at
these big tech company but I run Taro my
experience in terms of big Tech is I was
at meta or Facebook for four and a half
years where which is where I went from
senior to staff engineer prior of that I
was at Pinterest for two and a half
years and fun fact there is that I
actually got rejected I got rejected for
promotion twice at at Pinterest so I
feel like I have certainly been on both
sides of as a manager and I I've been on
both sides of getting promoted and i'
also been rejected multiple times from
promotion so happy to talk about that
too prior to Pinterest I was at a
startup which got acquired by Pinterest
so that's another fun story but yeah I
feel like we have tons of really smart
people here and really eager to to dive
in I just chime in like Rahul just
mentioned not getting promoted at Amazon
I've tried to get promoted to senior sd3
three times and failed all of them the
first try to get to L6 as a manager
failed that happens and also like
talking to the people on this panel like
a lot of people grew through these
levels super fast some changing
companies some being super successful
within their company whereas like I was
17 years 16 years into my career or
something when I made it to this level
so it's not a race certainly like if you
are succeeding and progressing through
the levels off but I just want to also
set the expectation that it's not like
what you are hearing from some people
here and maybe all of us might not be
your path so don't freak out if you've
missed a senior promo the first try like
that's not a weird thing so anyway yeah
no I appreciate that input we do have a
lot of great perspective here old young
not old you're not old more mature
perspective and younger perspective and
different companies and so on so I'm
super excited here how it's going to
work we have a couple questions that we
think will be broadly interesting to the
225 of you here and then after we go
through a couple of those I think
that'll probably take between 45 minutes
or an hour then at the end we will do
open question so you can raise your hand
and we'll call on you and you can unmute
okay so to get started the first
question that um we have is tell us what
the main project or perhaps multiple
projects that got you promoted to the
staff level into you anyone want to
start here I I'll go first I think so
for me I think there was two things
there because I was at Netflix and the
titles that everyone was just like
senior but I felt like I had staff
responsibilities and then I got promoted
by hopping company so I think it was the
Netflix project that Airbnb was like
okay this guy's staff level so I'm gonna
even though it wasn't a promoe I never
really got promoted there I got hired at
company but anyways going from that I
worked on this project at Netflix called
asset inventory and Netflix is famous
for having kind of microservice
architecture and one of the things
that's awesome about microservices is
you have this individual ownership one
of the things that's terrible about
microservices is security because then
it's oh instead of having one app to
hack now there's 3,000 or 4,000 or 5,000
apps to hack that each could have their
own different vulnerabilities and code
based problems and that was one of the
big nightmares that Netflix was trying
to figure out and the thing that I
worked on there was like I built this
graph database that described all of the
applications and code bases and data
sets and employees at the company and
how they're all connected and how they
all interact with one another and the
relationships between them it's like
this big ass knowledge graph of
everything and yeah I worked on that for
two years and that was a project was
really intense but yeah I would say that
was essentially what I worked on that
was like the thing that at least Airbnb
saw I was like yeah that's staff level
yeah so I'll hop been next I also wasn't
promoted I consider it's promoting
yourself when you've done the work and
you can convince someone someone else
that you're there and get hired that was
the direction I went but I had been
managing people for 3 years at Amazon
when I switched over to Facebook and at
and a staff level and so what I would
say is like doing the technical work was
not enough like being in a position to
lead people and know how to do that both
as an IC and as a people manager I think
is something that some people Overlook
they there are times where people are
like I but I delivered this huge project
and it had all this technical complexity
that's who else worked on it or how did
you plan that and how did you
parallelize those work streams how did
you like take risk prevention to make
sure the hardest thing wasn't the last
thing to get done and delay the project
and people are like I didn't have to I'm
indiv individually a genius and I
delivered it all myself and it's yeah
that's not necessarily meaning you're
there yet managing people and learning
to manage projects and work streams was
a big part of it at Amazon but before
that a lot of the work that I had done
as an IC that I think put me in a
position to speak about the technical
complexity when getting these other jobs
um mostly had to do with Android
internals um I was working on an app I
wasn't working on Android itself I
happen to be working on something that
is part of Google Play services which is
part of Android right now but in any
event at the time it was just like we
have these complicated apps and they
don't fit essentially
into the amount of it was a method limit
I don't know how familiar people are but
I had to write something that had a
custom class loader to allow us to use
multiple executable files in an Android
application before Google started
supporting that and put out something
that did that and that was like the most
technically complex thing that I had to
do to allow Amazon video which was what
I was working on it's Prime video now
and then like combination apps with the
shopping app and the App Store and video
like all the things in them like it
wouldn't work with just one and we
weren't going to tell Engineers like ah
put all the functionality into one big
method and have a switch statement on
the like operation or something like we
didn't want people to code dumb because
of this technical limitation so like
overcoming that and not just like having
a solution but making it work and
delivering that that app that could
continue to be extended was probably the
like biggest Tech project I'll kick it
to Ryan yeah
and you mentioned an interesting thing
which is being brilliant and shipping
everything yourself versus working in a
team for the staff level this is one of
the first levels where the Baseline
expectation is that you influence others
to get large undertakings that actually
built into the expectations of these
levels is that you're a leader and that
you're influencing people because
software is inherently collaborative and
so about the project that got me
promoted this work was a large
efficiency project it made video
processing at Instagram significantly
cheaper 94% cheaper for some of the
basic encodings that we produce and I
think a large part of what made this
project staff level and helped me get
promoted was that I created this scope
which meant that I went and I found it I
convinced people was a good idea I got
Buy in and then I led the execution on
it and going back to if I executed on it
personally I would step in for the most
critical components that added risk to
the project but in large part this
project was being executed on by several
engineers and I was bleeding and doing
the code review to make sure everything
came together in the end it's not just
me that worked on this project there's a
lot of other people that came together
to make this happen but I think the key
here that makes it staff level is like
the leadership and convincing everyone
that it's a good idea and going for um
so I'll pass it to Carly
hi interesting hearing all of you talk
about your Journeys because I've been
thinking about this a lot with my team
as well and it seems like what it takes
to get to the next level like everyone
has already said this is not just being
technically brilliant right it really
comes down to in my opinion in wars and
Trust for me I was obviously working on
a security project that's about as in
detailed that go but I was I had taken
ownership of a decent of a technical
piece of this project but
what I think and I had also I had hired
some one thought I had a direct report
under me and we were both kind of
attacking this problem from multiple
different angles I think what set me
apart and what led to my promotion to
staff was a couple of different things
number one I can actually pinpoint it
back to a presentation that I gave to an
executive leader in our company based on
some work that I had done as the
findings that I had uncovered and I
think being able to speak technically to
an audience that might not necessarily
want to sit in an engineering meeting
was something that really set me apart
from some of the other people that they
deal with who are working on highly
technical complicated problems and just
coming across as a trusted collaborator
and so out of that meeting I had an
opportunity to switch and so I didn't
change companies but I did do an
internal move to get to staff and that's
how I landed where I'm at now and so I
was actually interviewing or presenting
to someone in executive leadership and
as well as our CTO and he offered me a
job working for him after that
presentation and so we were able to make
that work it was really exciting for me
um because it opened up a lot more doors
for me I don't say that to say that's
normal you're not going to go into the
office of like Zuckerberg and kicked
down the door be like oh staff now but
at the same time you should be prepared
at a moment's notice be able to speak
eloquently to your work exactly like
what Lee said you should know your
numbers you should be able to recite
like the impact that you've had and you
need to be able to do this to Technical
and non-technical audiences and
oftentimes the people who are making the
decisions about whether or not you're
ready to move to the next level are both
so it's not just the fact that you can I
don't know do some crazy algorithm if
that you can actually speak to it to a
Layman make them understand and the
value in your work and I think that's
where you tip yourself over the Ed and
then of course there's all collaborative
nature of these projects right like it's
not just enough to be like oh I built a
machine learning model right like in my
case it needs to be larger scale
collaborative across a couple different
business units something that obviously
speaks to a pain point of the business
right I think everyone here universally
just described something that was
problematic for their company if you can
solve those problems like you're going
to be cheat up for Success all right are
you gonna be answering or
I'll time in here just because I feel
like I have a couple things that uh I
think might be helpful to people and
then for the future questions just in
the interest of throughput we don't all
have to answer you just whoever wants to
they can if they have something to say
they can answer but for this one I did
want to add to the great answers we
already heard I there were two projects
that got me promoted to stff engineer at
meta the first was actually an internal
tool that helped the debug ability of
the product I was working on and I was
able to quantify that it saved literally
thousands of hours of engineering time
throughout the course of the year and it
became effectiv like a platform where
other Engineers could add in their own
debug ability metrics their own debug
ability tooling into this kind of
architecture platform I built out so it
was really creating scope and allowing
other people to plug in that's a really
powerful way to have multiplicative
impact right and then on top of that I
had another project which was what I
would consider my main project which is
re architecting something about the
product I was working so a calling
architecture I was modernizing it to a
different team that had a set of API and
that's actually one of the lessons I
wanted to share is that one way to think
about getting promoted to these very
high levels is to think about a
portfolio of bets that you're making so
if you just have one project that you're
so hellbent on delivering that's a good
thing for the most part but in a big
tech company there are a lot of things
that frankly are not in your control and
so having one main project is what I did
along with one project which was more of
a internal tool or something that I had
a lot more control over that worked out
really well because in both of them in
tandem led to a huge amount of impact
right and you when you're blocked on one
you can work on the other that's one
thing I wanted to take away or share as
a takeaway is that you can actually
think about having maybe two or three
projects probably not 10 right you want
to have maybe two projects that you can
kind of balance between the other
comment I wanted to make here is like I
think Zach you mentioned this right that
you got hired in as a staff engineer at
Airbnb and that's another thing that's
worth calling out is that in in addition
to working hard and impressing all of
your colleagues and having enough impact
at your company another core ingredient
of getting promoted to a very senior
level is there needs to be sufficient
business need for that right there needs
to be scope that you can fill in to be a
staff engineer and frankly at some
companies which are not growing quickly
they're stagnant there may not be that
scope and so I think a lot of us are
talking here about getting promoted
internally I think that's certainly a
really uh good thing and we should all
drive for that but keep in mind that
there's also an opportunity to get
promoted simply by moving to a company
where there's a need for your skill set
yeah by the way on the portfolio of bet
that's a really interesting point if you
look at any promo packet it is a track
record of multiple halves worth of work
so it's not usually you're doing great
and all of a sudden you have a staff
project and boom you get promoted you've
usually been doing it for a while you
probably have some sort of track record
so that when your packet goes to the
promo committee people are aware of your
name and you've been doing near staff or
at staff level work for some time yeah
that is a great call out one thing I
just want to mention I dropped a link
similar to what Ryan did earlier I
dropped a link for uh video that I put
on Taro actually about a case study for
my promotion story so if that's
interesting to folks check that out
unless there's anything else to add here
I'll move on to the next question yeah I
think one thing I just want to add real
quick about the one of the things you
said rul that I love is multiplicative
impact so I like to think of if you're a
staff engineer at least like when I've
been working as a staff engineer like I
think of creating impact in two
directions you have like your vertical
impact of the direct impact that you
want to have on the business and then
you have a horizontal impact which is
how can I enable my team to move quicker
and how can I enable what about the
development process sucks and how can we
make the development process better and
thinking about not just what we are
building but how we are building it and
if you can do the if you can solve both
those how problems and the what problems
that's when people are like wow this guy
is really changing things and changing
how things work I know for me that was
like one of the other projects I worked
on that Netflix was I decided I was like
I want to learn some groovy script so I
can learn how to cut deploy times down
so then on my team I was able to write
this groovy script that cut down the jar
file that we deployed for our pipelines
and it removed all the unused
dependencies and it made it so that
depending on the project they either
saved 1 to seven minutes per deploy
which saved on average like an engineer
is going to deploy probably five or six
times a day when they're testing a
pipeline so it saves them like 30
minutes to an hour a day that's a lot of
like time that we get back if you and
then if you scale that out then it's
like more a matter of adoption than it
is of technical Excellence because then
all you have to do is scale that out and
get more people to adopt it and then
you're like see oh now I have a hundred
Engineers working and using this and
then it's okay wow that's freaking
that's how you can really also get a lot
of big impact as well yeah actually 66
people with a 16% increase is a 10x
engineer like you don't do 10x yourself
1% for a thousand people 10% for 100
that is where you actually make that
kind of impact in my opinion yeah
definitely and I've studied some
Engineers that are the L9 level which is
three levels higher than we're
discussing now these people are Legend
and looked at the things that they do
and often times they are just making
compounding improvements that make all
of meta faster and so imagine you make
the tooling that everyone's using 10%
better and there's five figures worth of
Engineers you're that's absurd impact
this definitely scills if you're
thinking even past staff level making
other people faster in large
organization that's a great segue
actually into a question that Brian had
and was a question I ask as well Brian
wrote for a staff engineer they often
will create or find their own scope or
problem but at the senior level one
level below you still need to do the
actual work of coding or implementing
something so how do you do both I think
the question if I could rephrase it is
how do you think about balancing the art
of delegating delegating work versus
doing it yourself I'll jump in here I
think that I this reminds me a lot of
conversations I had with my manager Jen
when I worked at Airbnb where each week
we would talk about are you managing
enough are you delegating enough are you
like working are you coding enough and
like to make sure that I was
contributing in each bucket enough
because I'm definitely someone who likes
to just nerd out and just like code
Scala all day and just get into the
nitty-gritty details of wow just really
get geeking out but then I do that I've
definitely been in that position where I
do that to the detriment of my team and
that's like a problem where I know I
need to be leaning more into leadership
those weeks and that's where having at
least for me having just very Frank
conversations with my manager about how
I'm spending my time makes me like and
then really taking her feedback in and
understanding like oh like I am not
leading enough and I need to be doing
more leadership at least for me that's
the bias U depending on the staff
engineer you might have one who's if if
a staff engineer is an engineer who came
from management they might have the bias
the other way around where they're like
peopling too much and they're not
drisking uh the technicals enough so
like you got you really want to learn
your own biases depending on your
background and if you know your own
biases are then you can try to adjust
for them to get into that kind of sweet
spot and that might not be 50/50 each
week you might not be like I did two and
a half days of leadership and two and a
half days of coding some weeks you might
do four days of coding in one day of
leadership and it might be the other way
around another week it like it really
depends on the balance that you're
trying to look for but there's also like
how you lead if you're doing deep
technical work you might be leading by
example you might need to be sharing
that out more you might need to be
pairing with some Junior people to be
divvying up work as you dive into it it
so they can follow some of the threads
instead of you having to do it all
yourself but like leading I this is one
of the things that I said when I was
like moving back and forth between IC
and management was like am I leading
from the front right now or am I leading
from the back am I pointing people the
direction they need to go or am I up
front and finding it and sending them
down the path with me and in terms of
that I think that you like how you lead
it it varies by team none of this stuff
is globally applicable some teams you're
like amongst peers that are all about
the same level as you how you lead that
team is way different than if it's all
new grads and you're the only person
that's been doing this for more than 20
minutes like how you lead yes getting
input from your manager can be really
helpful because they can be like yo you
spent the last three weeks and you did
get that 4% performance Improvement and
that's cool but no one understands how
you did it no one knows what's going on
like you didn't tell anyone what tools
you used and if you were hit by a bus
tomorrow we wouldn't even get it
committed so like you know how you do it
is as or more important than what you do
I think though true Le it makes me think
of how I would manage zap which is
actually a terrifying because I think we
would either have way too much fun or
kill each other but honestly I think
about with someone with Zach's Talent
right like he's obviously incredibly
successful and have the technical depth
that most people don't I would be remiss
if I let him go deep technically every
single day and no one really knows
exactly what he's doing like the force
multiplier for super like Zach will be
if I can get him into the R&D and design
if I can make sure that he has input in
all of the big projects that are going
on we understand Road mapap and we have
someone there who's be like that's going
to break that's going to get [__]
that's going to work and knowing being
able to do that quickly and then someone
else can get into the deep into the
schol and or depending on what it is and
he might need to step in in Hell
something really complicated but I think
that if I were in a position that's what
I would want from him because that where
he think that would be the most
effective use of his time but it's hard
because you also don't want to be in
meaningful day so it's a definite
balance something you have to talk to
your manager about something that came
out of what Carly just said is one of
the most powerful tools is asking the
right question at the right time you
being in the right place to hear someone
say that they're going to
rearchitecturing
that's not the right Focus we can put
that behind a shim and we can deal with
that later can be the difference between
successful projects and failing projects
if you don't have you know your senior
most people involved in those
discussions s they might call that out 3
or four months from now when you've
already sunk like two or three Dev years
into something and 20 minutes of their
time could have prevented that so like
where you are applying these I I don't
call people resources but where you're
applying these people time it can easily
like you know if they miss a hallway
conversation it can be costly they can't
be everywhere all at once but knowing
like this is going to be an important
thing this design matters like we need
eyes on it yeah I want to just add more
on that CU I like it really that
triggered my like beginning experience
at Airbnb because when I started there
they were like talking to me about we
need to get these profitability numbers
certified we need to do it that way and
it was like that was like the
stakeholders were really loud about that
and I was new so I was like okay I trust
you guys because when you're brand new
at a company you have to lean into
stakeholder requests until you get the
lay of the land s and I realized after
about six months there like listening to
these stakeholders and then learning
like more about and then I I finally got
the courage enough to ask what is the
fundamental difference if the if these
numbers are certified or not and like
the answer to that was like essentially
nothing or there was like one day
difference in delay and that didn't have
any like really strong fundamental
impact on the business whereas other
things we could be working on would and
so I actually told my manager at the
time I was like I spent six months on
that where we had like all the seniors
and me working on this trying to get
these numbers certified but it's a very
complicated pipeline that was not going
to happen and I was like yo this is like
a diminishing return I don't think we're
GNA like really get much value out of
working on this longer and like trying
to push this to the Finish Line even
though the stakeholders were really loud
about that and then I was like I think
we should change to focus on other
things that are going to have higher
impact and if you can explain the impact
of things like that can be awesome cuz
sometimes that can also save you a lot
of Dev headache like what Lee was saying
is if you could just show people how to
prioritize things then maybe you can
work on things that you enjoy more too
because those profitability metrics
those freaking those things almost ended
me at Airbnb so hard but like you and
three people working on that probably
for four months probably cost the
company a million plus dollars exactly
exactly salary not even like opportunity
cost totally it's that's a sunk cost not
and what was the opportunity that we
gave up for that and that's a thing that
I think is another big part about being
a staff engineer is you need to be able
to persuade and like convince and it's
because it's up to you you're the leader
here like you could you get to decide
what to work on a lot of the time your
manager leans on you to identify the
impacts and identify what things should
be worked on and it's also up to you to
recognize like what shouldn't be worked
on even if the stakeholders are loud
about it even if even if there's a lot
of people with a lot of opinions that
think that this is the right thing to do
so and you need to have that courage to
tell people like no we're de we're depr
prioritizing your thing even though I
know you're going to be mad about it
doesn't matter what it's not the highest
priority now and I think that and being
able to explain that thought process can
be wonderful and it helps your cross
functional Partners respect you more
because if especially if you
deprioritize their project but you don't
have a clear line of reasoning for it
then you're going to build a lot more
mistrust and you're going to build a lot
more kind of resentment potentially like
mistrust first then resentment if it
keeps happening and I've seen that
happen too where Team Dynamics have
fallen apart right where these
communications have not happened and so
that's definitely another skill that I
think is very important for success as a
staff engineer and one one last thing to
add so I think Lee you spoke a little
bit about the needs of the team and
maybe the needs of the project if there
is a lot of senior people on the project
it's going to completely change things
but if there's a lot of hand working on
execution maybe you're more in a
leadership capacity one thing that I'd
like to add is also it depends on your
strengths as well so there are some
Specialists or people who are
ridiculously productive or just them
execute is worth like four or five
Engineers those people can have staff
level impact by doing all the execution
themselves they are still expected to
scale themselves by sharing their
knowledge and those types of things but
they may be doing Almost 100% the
execution themselves because they're
ridiculously productive or maybe they're
specialist and no one else can do their
exact work it it depends it depends on
your strength not everyone the tech lead
archetype some people are just heads
down coder some people people are domain
specialist yeah isn't isn't that the
archetype you're describing there I
swear I remember at meow when I was
there I was like they had the like the
code monster AR type code machine I love
that one for sure that's great for sure
I feel I relate to that a lot for sure I
don't that we answered this question at
all I think we had a super interesting
conversation but I don't know that we
answered like where you find and make up
this scope I I the thing is that that
gets bandied about because you start to
get better than the people that are
managing you at your job and they can't
find these things anymore they can't
know what the sort of landmines are in
your project they can't know what
technical things are actually
constraining projects anymore and so
that's where the like you need to invent
it is like you don't need to make up
something to get promoted like that is a
bad choice you need to identify the
things that are hurting and that are
holding the team back and raise those
things up and convince people to get
them done and do them and that is where
you're like inventing quote unquote this
scope is I I consider it like was
calculus invented or discovered like I
would say it was discovered and so are
these like pieces of scope that you need
to come up with you may invent something
brand new and convince people to do it
but most often you're discovering the
things that must be done that either
other people are afraid of they don't
see they don't think are valuable and
you are in the position that you have to
convince them that they are going to
actually accelerate the next three
projects if you take this on right now
or they're going to enable something
that the product couldn't do before so
that to me like I heard this a lot of oh
it's up to you to find the scope and was
like that's not a cool thing where am I
going to find this scope and it like
turns out that it is in the sort of
either archaeology or Discovery in the
code or whatever or not even code like
in product requirements that you like
find that there is a gap and one of the
big things that I've done throughout my
career that sometimes help sometimes
doesn't is be the one that puts my hand
up when no one else will it's a this old
rickety system it sucks no one wants to
work on it we should probably turn it
off and it's oh you know what actually
that's generating hundreds of millions
of dollars in Revenue we probably
shouldn't turn it off we should probably
find like Strangler fig pattern to
gradually replace it with something
modern or whatever but no we're not
going to give up on this system or leave
it to the analysts to try to keep it
running like it matters so those sorts
of things again sometimes you get stuck
with something awful when you are doing
that but yeah anyway we'll be done yeah
actually I'll use that as a transition
point to the next question but just Lee
I love what you said I feel like one way
of summarizing that is if you're asking
yourself the question how do I find
scope to justify my promotion to staff
engineer I feel like you've already lost
but that's the wrong question to ask the
correct question to ask is what are the
most burning problems in this or what is
the top of- mind concern for my manager
director other Engineers on the team and
can I build something or figure out a
solution to this problem that will help
everyone and you can derive from that
the necessary scope to get promoted but
if you start with hey how can I be like
The Village Idiot stumbling around to
find scope you're probably not going to
find it it's like building a startup in
some ways you don't go out and say like
where what is the problem like you don't
start with a solution you start with the
problem and then from there you derive
the solution so you don't start with
okay what is the someone a bill it
should be educated by the people you
talk to and part of talking to people is
relationship building right like you
have to be pretty embedded in the
organization to figure out what those
problems are and so that's the next
question I wanted to bring up at the end
of the day in a big Tech organization we
have to be honest that there is some
level of politics that when you go in
for your performance review you have to
get a review from someone you might have
mentored maybe someone who's a tech lead
or a manager on the team and they going
to talk about hey here here's what Ryan
did in the past six months and here's
why it was exceptional he should get
promoted or whatever the the phrasing
might be and so I'm curious for all of
you how deliberate were you about that
relationship building in terms of hey
I'm going to find someone who I can
mentor and they're going to write good
things about me in my performance review
or vice versa like here is a director
who I really want to impress that can
say good things about me performance
review either upward or downward I'm
curious how you all thought about
relationship building it's the most
important thing you can do man down at
least in my experience how did you go
about doing that Carly were there one-on
ones that you set up recurring with
different people or how did you um
identify people who you wanted to really
build that relationship with usually
it's people that I interact with who I
think we have some sort of common
approach or common problem and we end up
sinking up trying to solve something
together I will say that at my current
organization I have people that I would
probably consider friends all over the
org in various business units people I
probably don't even talk to every single
day or interact with on a daily basis
through my normal work and people are
always surprised to say oh I didn't know
and I'm like I know [__] but that's
part of it right but if you want to be
seen as an expert within your
organization people need to know who you
are around the whole of w and like if
you hide all day if you're remote way
harder I love working remote but I got
to say doing that while I've been remote
full-time at after since I started was
significantly more difficult than when I
was in a in an office
for so it was extremely intentional it
was Finding commonalities with people
striking up friendships like the day Bly
if you don't have people you can like
[__] talk with on slack too so a lot of
it is just for fun because what are we
all here doing if not trying to get
through our day but then those people
are the ones that you can rely on when
you need something and they know that
they can rely on you as well and so if
you're super introverted I totally get
it i' say that I'm probably an
introverted extrovert you need to go
against every fiber in your being that's
telling you like don't talk to this
person don't DM them don't bother them
they don't want to talk to you and
really try to build bir relationships CU
you're never going to thrive in your
career if nobody knows who you are
because who is going to step up and say
that you're great at at anything that
person doesn't exist no one's going to
come to your rescue and see you heads
down at 10 p.m. on slack just cuz your
little thing is green and say holy moly
Zach deserves a promotion no they're
going to say Zach deserves a promotion
because everyone knows that he's a rock
star because in every meeting he's
absolutely killing it is delivering he's
showing up delivering his timelines
everything is on scope everything is
within budget right like all of those
things come to the table and you need
those people crouching for you so
thinking that someone's going to save
you is the wrong approach and I see a
lot of people doing that like one day
they'll notice me right no if only I put
in another 70h hour week for sure will
know that I'm full person always metal
or trophy like yeah your code will not
speak for itself your code will not
speak for itself yeah yeah when it comes
to networking or getting people to know
your work I did a really bad job of
going to happy hours and I think even
when we were in person and building
relationships I didn't do a super good
job but my work was very visible and I I
got the promotion even during covid so I
think this might apply for people who
are asking about how to get promotion
while remote and really the number one
thing is that you communicate your work
the plan get Buy in you tell people how
great the results were I know in Ideal
World you just have impact you don't
need to tell people for it to matter but
that's not how prussians work people
need to know who you are how good your
work was that's why communication and
writing are really exceptional tools if
you're looking to grow your career
because it's not enough to quietly have
and in theory if you are do make doing
such a good job your work will Market
itself but it's always helpful to put
the extra work your your code and your
work cannot Advocate on your behalf to
people like maybe if it's an internal
tool people are using it and your name
is on it like maybe but maybe your
manager can be your cheerleader but
eventually you're going to run out like
they will not be able to do it for you
anymore for me like being known is been
the biggest difference between stuck at
L5 never going to get anywhere to I'm
pulling together Android Engineers from
across Amazon asking if they've had the
same problem giving them the data on
when their app is about to run out of
methods and saying we've got to fix this
does anyone else have anything okay
reader team you moved Lucine to a
separate deex file so you could use that
but that's the only thing and you only
did it like this and it's super
self-contained okay cool that's one step
but what else are we going to do and
then whenever there's something going on
it's oh hey yeah I know who's on the App
Store that worked on that go talk to
them being able to be the person people
go to and if you don't know the answer
you can give them a single step from you
to the answer that's incredibly useful
and this sounds like oh you're just like
being a social butterfly no like human
relationships are all there is none of
this matters without that whether it's
the relationship with our customers our
users our co-workers those that we
supporting that are you know underneath
us whether we're managers or not like
that is all that matters no one is going
to remember that cool for Loop you wrote
10 years from now they're going to
remember the time that like you
introduced them to the right person to
get them the opportunity that they
needed or that you gave them the advice
that avoided them like getting stuck in
a horrible project like that's what
matters it is all people so for me like
I am remote I didn't go and visit when I
was at meta at all and I failed like I
did not succeed there I had decent
relationships with the people I was
supporting and they thought I was a cool
person but it didn't matter like I
didn't have the visibility I didn't have
the relationships I didn't have the
relationships once things started going
bad to get the help I needed to dig my
way out I had a mentor and was like what
you're doing is great I don't know why
the team is like this and that was it I
didn't have anyone else meeting people I
will say this is also like a scaling
thing where we've talked about going
broad I've started like when I was at
Amazon with my own team asking one like
off-topic question every day during the
pandemic and now since then that hybrid
and remote work is normal just so we
have something to talk about just so
we're like engaging with each other
socially and now I've moved from the
chat organization to the Gmail
organization all of the chat
organization and all of Gmail front end
I now in two different rooms ask this
question every day and engage with
people I will run into people when I'm
in Sunny Veil hey you're the question
person hell yeah I'm the question person
you don't know anything else about me
you don't even know I'm a software
engineer but my name and if I came to
you I was like hey you're a PM in the
spaces org and I need help with this
they'd be like oh yeah I know you let's
talk and not find a Time on my calendar
next month so it does not have to be
that you are working on a project
together that you build a relationship
with someone like you can say like to a
manager hey is there anyone on your team
that needs a mentor like even if the
answer is no you asking that question
changed how they think about you like
you going and hanging out with the PMS
at one meeting during their Summit just
to understand their process and see if
you can contribute and say hey if you
had a Dev representative here it might
be really helpful or if you like at this
stage brought someone in it could change
the way that we approach like writing
our stories or whatever process you use
and then all the PMS are like that's a
cool person I like them and it has
changed the dynamic and changed your
sort of social cache and a sign ific way
and I know some people are like this
sounds like politics or playing a game
and what I will say is maybe it does and
it's not all bad sometimes you have to
play the game and playing games is fun
sometimes I will also note that I am an
autistic person and I have lots of
Social Challenges and yet I have found
out that if I don't do this I cannot
succeed I've got to figure it out and
sometimes I figure that out by finding
ways to be a weirdo and bringing people
into the weirdness that works to just do
make friends
Weir there's so much I want to add two
things there's so much good knowledge
being dropped here if you all are
getting value out of this just to give
us some feedback can you just drop a
reaction a thumbs up just to let us know
if this resonating two things I want to
add to so much good stuff that just was
said one thing that Lee mentioned I
think a good litmus test for if you are
getting staff level or any kind of
seniority in your company is if I go to
your teammate and say hey what are what
is this person what is Ryan known for in
the team or in the organization and they
can't tell me cohesively okay here's
what Ryan did here's what Lee did here's
what Carly did that's a bad sign like
they should say oh Ryan is the person
he's the expert on this system if I have
a question about that I have a bug I
have a concern he can help me out that
is I think a really good way of of
evaluating if you've built up that brand
that credibility among your team or or
so I think that's one thing I want to
call out the other thing is there were a
couple comments like Sean said what
happened to modesty in this day and age
so my rebuttal to that Sean is don't
think of this as self-promotion like I
did this project let me go tell everyone
how awesome I am that's not the right
way to view it in my opinion the correct
way to view it is hey the work I've done
has value to you as my teammate I can
make your life better I can make the
company moreone money I can make our end
users happier and experience your bug
there's value in the work I'm doing and
therefore I would like you to be in
informed of how you can benefit from my
work for example this debug ability
thing that I built at meta was a big
part of my promotion I built a tool that
improved how quickly you could debug
issues in the product I worked on when I
went and went out and talked about it I
said hey here's a tool that will make
your life easier and in fact I have a
way for you to also get impact on your
performance review this going to help
you and it'll help the product it'll
help everyone and so one way to think
about it is what is a call to action
you're not going out just to Pat
yourself on the B you're trying to go
out there and say hey here are ways you
can get plugged in here are ways that
you can help yourself or you can help
the team and if happens to be the work
that I did because the work I did is
valuable and I want to tell you about it
so that's how I would reframe this idea
of self-promotion I can tell you're a
startup founder you were made for it I
completely support sex work so this
isn't a negative thing but you sharing
knowledge is not prostitution you
sharing knowledge has Mutual benefit it
helps everyone for you to say this is
the thing I did it was hard when I tried
it this way and it only worked when I
did this I ran into a problem over here
and this is how I solved it if you need
to build something like this the like
the first thing I did was build a lower
level framework for it that you can
share like changes the usefulness of
your work it is not like Shameless
bragging you're not like wearing a metal
yeah you can wear a metal if you want
but like you are not just doing it to
show off you're doing it because it
matters and like your work is important
yeah and you're preventing future pain
too it's I don't know I feel like
sometimes Engineers feel like the only
way to learn things is the hard way
through debugging and crying and if you
share your knowledge there's another way
that you can maybe teach people right
you can teach people through all sorts
different ways and i' I definitely think
that's a big thing where it's okay are
you I think that there's a difference
here it's an interesting line between
like bragging and teaching where it's I
think that's the line that some people
like feel like they might be Crossing
sometimes as an engineer but it's I know
if you ever do a lunch and learn when
you're teaching people stuff like
there's going to be Engineers who don't
know this stuff I I know whenever I did
the lunch and learns when I sat in on
them I'm like wow I just learned like 10
things and it's and most Engineers are C
curious open-minded T tenacious people
cuz it's if you're in big Tech you they
select for those traits a lot of the
time so they're going to want to hear
what you have to say anyways let you
learn someone can be doing a demo and
that they have a browser extension that
makes it so much easier and like what
the hell where did you and they're like
oh yeah I wrote that thing I only use it
and it's like you post it can you share
that because that's rad like you just
like someone's sharing their screen for
15 minutes can change the way you look
at doing work and they like they may not
know what it's a cool thing so I don't
know there's lots of ways that like
sharing is caring and they'll do it cool
so we have half an hour left okay so
here's what I'm thinking I have one more
question I'd love to get your input on
we can try and keep it relatively short
maybe five or six minutes and then for
the remaining 20 25 minutes I'd love to
open up to the audience and see if
there's a burning question we can answer
from the crowd but the question last
question on my end is what heuristics
can you tell us about that optimizing
chance for promotion especially the
staff level engineer and what I mean by
that is when you think about a team or
an or which is likely to get you
promoted do you think about oh I want to
go to a team which is very Junior heavy
very senior heavy small large team how
about infrastructure team versus product
team that's a really interesting thing
where I think a lot of people in
Industry talk about how there's a
frontend feeling it's actually harder to
have multiplicative impact when you're
doing a widget on the Android app
compared to If You're Building backend
infrastructure WI impacting hundreds of
Engineers so I'm curious for each of you
what heuristics do you have to think
about where it's more likely to get that
staff level promotion talk to someone
that's above staff level senior staff or
principal ask them what in this or they
would fix if they had more time and then
do that they know where the problems are
they don't have the time to do all of it
you fix a problem that they had a
problem with and and you have a
principal writing support on your promo
document that's going to go a long way
beyond that find out what's missing
submit a document before it's ready or
at least have people that are on the
Committees that review them or managers
that review them whatever the process is
at your company write your doc right now
not when you think it's ready write it
right now and take it to people and say
why would you reject this and then start
working on that
you may not be able to like get that
work right away your manager may not buy
in on it whatever but if you don't know
what you're missing and you think this
project that you're about to work on is
your promo project and you do it and
it's not you're going to be pissed and
it's your fault you didn't find out
beforehand if it's actually matters and
if you were actually missing it so find
out oh you know what no all the projects
you've done are great but we've never
seen you lead anyone we've never seen
you present anything then you're like oh
[__] like this next project I don't need
to write a bunch of code I need to be
the one that makes it better and makes
it sure it's on time and that other
people say yeah they we were able to
knock that out of the park because this
person was leading it but if you're
going blind you will not figure out you
will not hoen your way into the
promotion like the process itself is
beastly and if you don't understand it
you're not going to get promoted and if
you think I'm not a manager I don't need
to understand it then you probably
aren't going to get promoted unless your
manager is an incredible person and that
happens sometimes but that is luck that
is not something that you can affect I
think we all wish we were our for now I
do I follow churn that's my jam at every
company of work that I always do those
are were my projects I over induct them
R though paino in the business always so
dealing with churn for most of the
companies I've been at we rely on
subscribers users whatever so yeah I
always try to solve something related to
sure something Financial for the
business and that's where I've always go
I think for me I think that there's a
couple different characteristics that I
like to think about like for if you're
going to get promoted and all that stuff
I always think that the number one her
istic that Rahul like I think is missing
here is your relationship with your
manager if you don't have a good
relationship with your manager like it's
going to be hard it's just going to even
if you're the most Rockstar amazing guy
ever like it's not going to happen I but
like when I think about like big team
small team stuff like that data
engineering has a different perspective
here a little bit where it's the data
sets that you're using and creating as a
data engineer like there better be like
30 other pipelines that read from it if
there's not it's not going to be theft
level engineer you got to have you're
not creating like the data set that is
used to make a viz you need to be making
the data set that then everyone else
makes other data sets with like you got
to create that Master data if you're not
creating Master data you're not a staff
engineer a staff data engineer and you
might be a staff analytics engineer if
you do things end to end where you do
logging to data set to viz and you and
and maybe ml model and you have all four
of those and you go more horizontally
like that then that's another way that
you can potentially be like staff level
but at least for like the data engineer
family if you aren't creating Master
data and not not servicing a lot of
teams with that Master data like you're
probably not at that staff level yet and
for me I I withraw the hero stics from
the rubric that everyone uses to discuss
what is staff and higher scope and
typically like when we talk about those
projects there's three characteristics
like typically how large is the size of
the work stream it's usually Quantified
with the number of Engineers involved
the duration the complexity of the work
stream can someone in the level below
you not solve that problem for some
reason whether like some specific domain
expertise on distributed systems or AI
or something like that and then the last
thing is like the actual impact of the
effort is it Banning multiple teams is
it achieving like significant business
goals for the ore and so the reason that
I mentioned this is because I think like
what Zach was mentioning is like talking
about getting leverage by building data
sets that everyone else is using that
means that this is going to have a lot
more impact because you're making one
data set here and then everyone's
building on top of it so you're one
level will higher up in this you know
leveraged impact that you can get if
there's opportunities for you to build
things that are enabling others to build
on top of them that's going to get you
more of that leverage impact or if
you're building tooling or anything like
that so that will bias a little bit more
towards the infrastructure teams if
you're going that route if you're trying
to go for like the workstream size route
there's limited spot for that if you
want to be the main lead in charge of
this massive product initiative let's
say that's 50 people involved there's
only one spot for that top person to be
the you know main Tech lead so those
roles are a little the senior engineer
and not like a staff or principal
engineer that gets picked to do that
like why would they trust you with it
and maybe you've built up the like
credentials and maybe you've built up
the trust but you're like right there at
the promotion Point like you probably
don't need that project to get promoted
if they're willing to hand it to you I
don't know that's a rough one yeah
exactly those types of promotions
require permission someone's got to say
you're the in charge so there's less of
those roles available and they're harder
to compete for but there's definitely
some opportunities but most of these
really senior Engineers I see are more
on the infrastructure side or tooling or
and it's specifically because of that
leveraged impact if you're building on
that bottom layer you're making everyone
better I want to kick it to live
questions but I just want to say this
infro thing and backend thing to me is a
legacy bias we just don't know as much
what it looks like for people to perform
at this level in other places we've seen
what it looks like for backend systems
to support billions of users and there's
lots of people that understand that and
the complexity when you're working on
it's better now but if 10 years ago you
were working on an Android app no one
knew what it looked like for a senior
staff engineer to be doing that work
what is the difference between what
they're doing with this application and
what someone else would be doing they're
like tremendously complex apps billions
of people might be using them but no one
really quite understands what principal
front end engineer or something does and
so if no one can judge it and no one can
measure it you better switch to a
backend team so you can get your promo
which is [__] but it has been a real
thing so that's very true also in data
engineering I've noticed that like when
I was working at Facebook in 2016 there
was uh one there was one staff data
engineer now there's tons but this is
because data engineering was very new
like data engineering was like maybe 5
years old at that point in 2016 and so
there wasn't like a lot of good
definition of what those roles look like
and then now there's probably dozens and
dozens of Staff data engineers at
Facebook but back then there was
literally one yeah oh one thing I just
want to add the the infrastructure bias
doesn't necessarily mean front end
versus backend there are Engineers that
build client side infrastructure like
maybe the build system that's used on
Android or maybe there's some framework
that is used to manage requests between
the client and server so that could
still be on the front end but it's still
infrastructure like product
infrastructure the key is that you have
the other Engineers that are leveraging
what you build and that usually one
layer lower than the person who's
building the user facing experience
unless you're one of those whober techly
building some new
product before we open it up to the
audience anyone else want to mention
anything otherwise the way it'll work is
there should be a raise hand
functionality in Zoom so if you want to
ask a question you can go ahead now and
raise your hand hey thank you for the
discussion um wondering if you have any
advice I'm already at staff level what
would you recommend
to with regard to Performance Management
I'm finding that exceeding expectations
at this level is becoming harder and
harder that's my question I can speak a
little bit about that that so you're it
sounds like you're talking about teener
staff once you get to the staff level
teor staff and higher the behaviors are
actually very similar you are
influencing through others you are
growing other people around you and
you're often taking on the largest
problems in your or the number one thing
that changes is just that the
initiatives you take on are one step
bigger or one step more impactful or
something like that so it depends on
your specific or or are you an
infrastructure engineer or what exactly
but you just need to do exactly what you
have been doing and if you are on the
exceed side as a staff engineer it's
just a matter of finding something that
is even larger in scope so instead of
influencing your group of your or that's
like maybe 50 people maybe you're um
influencing across two larger orbs or
maybe you're building some new
infrastructure that hundreds of
Engineers are using instead of maybe
just like dozens of Engineers so um it's
just a matter of scaling and taking on
more scope but it very similar behaviors
I want to add just a little bit to that
so before I quit my job at Airbnb I got
exceeds at the staff level for my last
like for 2020 and here was the
perspective that like you want to do to
think about like the different projects
that I was working on so if you want to
get the staff level usually or exceeds
you're going to want to deliver on like
your main mey project for me that was
pricing and availability and getting
those metrics like really refined really
good they run your highquality big rock
project but then you should also be
working on designs and discussions for
like longer term things so like one of
the things I worked on was this document
on how we should build best practices on
how to take data from the data Lake and
put it back into the Airbnb app and the
best practices around that and getting
feedback from Principal engineers and
all the other Engineers like in the
company to understand like what they're
what kind of edge cases we could we run
into and what are the different like use
cases and patterns that are involved
there and if you can get one of those
kind of like higher level architecture
impacts as well as like just the meaty
like big rock impact that is like you if
you don't deliver that you're not going
to even meet expectations if you can do
both of those things that's how you're
going to really get to that next level
that like senior staff sort of level
that's great let's move on to
Alan my question is related to what
seems to be like the most recurring
piece of advice Beyond just a sheer
technical skill which is doing that sort
of technical communication both to
people who are non-technical and also
people who are technical as well as
building those relationships and
mentorship and I was wondering if you
have any advice or resources books
articles whatever that you found helpful
for just building that sort of
communication and finding mentorship
within your org or without your org that
makes sense yeah I can I can chime in
here quickly I think one of the core
skills of communication is know who
you're talking to so I'll talk about
meta or Facebook which is where I was
from almost 5 years they're a workplace
group and so one thing that I did before
I posted any so workplace is basically
like an internal version of Facebook you
would post updates about your work and
keep people informed and so one thing I
would do before I posted anything is I
would look through the membership and
say hey is this workplace primarily
other Engineers is it the leadership
team is it a cross functional group of
marketers and PMs and engineers and
based on that you should tailor the
level of depth of your communication to
accommodate that I think you have to be
really careful not to go too deep in the
weeds or too light on the detail either
extreme is not good depending on who
you're talking to and so core part of is
number one research who's in the standup
or the meeting or the workplace group
that you're addressing and number two
understand how much do they know are you
if there like a PM that you're talking
to how much do they actually know about
your work how much do they care and
based on that you should accommodate or
message differently I don't really have
a book or a video recommendation off the
top of my head I will say just talking
to people again is really important to
you because you want to have some
empathy for where are they coming from
what are they trying to get done and the
way you do that is again going back to
what we talked about 15 minutes is
relationship building understand who
they are and how you can help them and
then if you do that enough you get a
good sense of the different personas
that you're talking to I think one thing
that I just want to add real quick is
one thing that I noticed that was this
weird unexpected Synergy for me when I
was working at Airbnb was so I when I
worked at Airbnb I made
a LinkedIn post almost every single day
and one of the things that you'll learn
about the LinkedIn algorithm is that uh
it really rewards conciseness and if you
can tell people dense information in the
most concise way possible yeah that is a
very powerful skill and and it's even
more than like the level of detail but
even if you have the level of detail can
you say it in a way that is still
concise but detail that is another thing
that I would highly recommend that you
can learn to grow from but that's
another great way to learn let's move on
to
sesh hi thank you R for doing all of
this so my question is you have talked
about a lot about how impact a staff
careers can bring in but I am a senior
software engineer I want to become a
tech lead soon I want to ask you like
what will be my progress if I want to go
to Tech lead first and then probably St
engineer later yeah I can speak a little
about this it's interesting that you
mentioned Tech lead as its own level
separate from senior and staff because I
view Tech lead as a set of behaviors
that can happen across level so there
are senior Engineers that work on teams
that are Tech lead they lead smaller
project but they do everything that you
expect from a tech it I don't know if
that answers your question exactly but
if you're trying to grow from senior you
can take a look at like your specific
companies like leveling system and I
think you'll see that a lot of companies
Tech leadership is just like a set of
behaviors that can is orthogonal the the
level that you're I just want to cut in
real quick I think that if what you're
missing if you've gotten feedback and
what you're missing on promotion is some
of these leadership things and some of
these visibility things maybe being a
tech lead will put you in a position to
do more of that but it doesn't mean it's
a stepping stone necessarily like you
doing those behaviors and being a strong
Tech lead does not mean you know that
you're on your way to staff necessarily
yeah this also shouldn't be like a
something that's a mystery to anyone
like Ryan said there should be a
leveling system at your company or
behaviors are clearly defined for each
level and you should be able to look at
it and have a conversation with your
manager about where you're exceeding and
where you're deficient none of us will
be able to tell you exactly what all of
those behaviors are most companies
there's some standards but it might be a
little bit different and if you don't
know that for your company that's a
really good place to start and ask for
that documentation because you can only
guess you really need to get that
outlined for you let's do one last
question before we each give our
concluding remarks uh Sam rude hi guys
nice talking to you all thanks for doing
this I'm a big fan of Zach data
engineering is my thing so I want to
know one thing exact from you so I've
been working in data engineering for
five years now so one thing is I'll be
working on a different manager my
project manager is different and my Vine
manager and the whole setup is different
where I am reporting to so for the P for
the performance review I have to take
what what all I have done to my manager
or the reporting manager it would be a
very tedious task to explain him what I
have done since he's not managing me and
as a data engineer like most of the
things I'll coding and all the backend
work it this can be applicable to the
backend Engineers as well so I don't
even for the fact that to put something
in my portfolio I don't have any
anything to show in the front end so how
do you manage this how do you showcase
yourself at the great question yeah so I
I got you on this so so part of this is
if you don't have a portfolio piece
something shiny or flashy to put in
front of people like part of that is on
the data scientist to help you bring
that to the end or the data analyst to
give you that front end experience if
it's a viz project so that's one way
that like you can sell yourself I think
another way is like what are the other
Downstream impacts for example for me
when I worked at Airbnb one of the big
things was is I worked on the pricing
and availability data sets which then
got put into Smart Pricing which is an
algorithm that picks prices for Airbnb
listings and that had a very big impact
on the business so that usually it's
there's like your data sets can be sold
as they make one of three people make a
decision better it's either they make an
executive better at making a strategic
decision they make a data scientist or
data analyst better at making a product
decision or they make a machine learning
algorithm better at making an automated
decision
and if one of those three things is
better there's usually a metric behind
it behind like that kind of stuff
sometimes the analytical work doesn't
have as much of a metric because it's
more an increased visibility but trying
to craft a story behind that visibility
can be another great thing to do because
it will help show show things off that
way and one last thing I would say is
that as a data engineer you always have
the optimization metrics that you can
look at like this pipeline is now 30%
faster or 40% faster because one of the
bigest things I did at Airbnb for the
pricing and availability data sets is I
cut their size by 90% And the whole
company can then use a data set that's
10 times smaller and so that was another
way I sold my impact but it's a tricky
problem because data engineering has
that kind of issue where it does fall
into the Shadows a little bit and it
doesn't have as much of that shiny
frontend appeal to it that you can't
show it off as much as you can show off
a squl query I don't know so I think
that'd be my kind of perspective on like
to like sell your impact as a data
engineer okay awesome so unfortunately I
think we're going to end the questions
here I'm going to start with Ryan and
we're going to ask everyone on the panel
to just say where can people follow up
with you or if you have any concluding
remarks uh Ryan you can go go ahead and
start yeah thanks rul for doing the
question asking and organizing
everything that was really awesome
thanks so much to my fellow panelists it
was great meeting all I see you all on
LinkedIn but this first time actually
putting a face to the name so it's
really great and I really appreciate
everyone listening and just the showing
was really awesome I feel like I always
just interact through like comments and
stuff so this is really welcome
interaction where you can follow me at
mainly post on LinkedIn and the other
thing that I do is I write a substack
which kind of has a lot of content
that's about software engineering career
growth and all that I'll put the link in
the chat there so yeah thanks everyone
for listening yeah Ryan substack is pure
just Solid Gold by the way so so good
it's so it's so good it's so good
definitely definitely definitely uh
subscribe to that I'll pass it to uh Z
awesome thanks thanks everyone for uh
coming to this I'm like amazed that we
were able to get like 200 I think we
were at Peak and we like 260 people in
here it's freaking nuts and for me it's
I'm mostly on LinkedIn and Twitter uh I
do reals as well reals and Tik toks so
if you want to get me there too that's
great I'm finally understanding reals
and Tik toks they are a weird one and
yeah I do substack as well that's why I
do more long form data engineering stuff
I'm mostly talking about data
engineering right now but in the future
in the next sixish months I'm going to
be doing more software engineering
content as well and like software
engineering data product content like
similar if youall ever read the book
designing data intensive applications I
want to build boot camps that teach that
in a very applied way but anyways I have
the two domains that I would recommend
y'all check out I have exactly. substack
docomo and that's going to be more
I bought the domain I spent the money I
spent the money how much was that domain
that's a really good domain was like
seven Grand that bad it honestly was not
that bad yeah I'll pass it to Lee yeah
so I right first off yes thanks everyone
for coming this is a great turnout good
questions everything it was a great
conversation I am have just started like
within the last couple of weeks the
substack I've been writing on LinkedIn a
lot but it's a very hard platform for
people to discuss discover old content
on and such even though I was like super
fastidiously like keeping a link tree up
to date for a while it didn't matter no
one used it so for a long timely yeah so
it's been about a year and I have
written a lot of things so I'm trying to
find a way to recycle those and shiny
them up potentially on substack so um
come see me I toss the link into the
chat you can easily find me on LinkedIn
my name is fairly unique so yeah we've
got Carly left and rul so Carly you're
up Hey
awesome hey everybody you can find me on
LinkedIn uh I'm also on Instagram Carly
machine learning I don't do any link act
do I just mostly PR real I think that
are funny but I think we all need that
in our lives you can also find me
playing Call of Duty um I'm sorry ahead
of time for smoking you yeah that's
mostly it this was super fun uh right R
all right yeah so once again thank you
to everyone who joined and thank you to
the panelists it's so much fun I feel
like all interacted online in in some
asent capacity but it's super fun to see
all four of you in this more real time
way I want to say two things one is a
piece of advice and then the other is I
want to plug something right so in terms
of one takeaway at least for me is I
think the vast majority of people when
they are aiming for staff engineer or
any senior engineer they the 99% of
Engineers are lacking when it comes to
relationship building and talking to
people it's not about the code it's
about really figuring out what are the
problems who are the people who are
encountering those problems and how can
you solve them so I think that's in my
opinion one thing that I really would
love for people to take away from this
conversation in terms of lugging stuff I
have a YouTube channel I have been
trying to be better about higher quality
content there in terms of like really
fit the algorithm so I'd love for you to
get give feedback there if you have any
and yeah LinkedIn is also I'm pretty
active there so I think that's it I
think we have to have two follow-ups
number one is back we need to hear about
your Burning Man Saga and then number
two if you all are okay with that you
can do like round two of the staff
engineer panel in another month or two
but this is super fun whoops all Q&A
yeah whoops all Q I'm so down I'm so
down this is absolutely wonderful yeah
cool okay this is super fun thank you
again to everyone have a great evening
bye everybody bye